Mobile: +31 (0) 623105600

Summary

I am a PhD student at Wageningen University & Research (WUR), the Netherlands. I am enthusiastic about coupling computational tools with chemical/physical/materials science knowledge to gain insights into some of the most fundamental processes. Specifically, in my PhD, I am studying fundamental reactions involved in the conversion of biobased-feedstock to platform chemicals for biofuels. The goal is to design cheap-and-efficient catalysts for biomass conversion. For this, I use knowledge of chemical/physical science and mathematical modelling to run computer simulations. For such simulations, the underlying theories are the widely used computational approaches like density functional theory (DFT), ab initio molecular dynamics (AIMD), microkinetic modelling (MKM), etc. I am also interested in learning to accelerate these approaches by the means of machine learning (ML) and artificial intelligence (AI) tools. Apart from research, I play, and intensively follow, football, and I am also learning to play piano & guitar.

Research interests

Computational materials science, surface science, heterogeneous catalysis, and application of data science & machine learning in catalysis design and discovery.

Research experience

Oct 2020 - Present	Doctoral Student at Wageningen University & Research (WUR), The Netherlands Supervisors: Prof. Han Zuilhof & Prof. Harry Bitter & Prof. Guanna Li Biobased Chemistry and Technology (BCT) & Organic Chemistry(ORC), WUR Topic: Multiscale modelling of transition metal carbide catalysts for biomass conversion.
May 2019 - May 2020	Master Thesis Student- Advisors: Prof. Michele Casula and Prof. Prasenjit Ghosh Université Pierre et Marie Curie (UPMC), (IMPMC) - Sorbonne University, France Topic: Magnetic properties of narrow zigzag graphene nanoribbons from <i>ab initio</i> calculations.
August 2018 - May 2019	Research Intern- Advisor: Prof. Prasenjit Ghosh, Department of Physics Indian Institute of Science Education and Research Pune, India Topic: Electronic structure calculations of solid materials using Quantum ESPRESSO.
May 2018 – July 2018	Summer Research Intern- Advisor: Prof. Eluvathingal D. Jemmis Indian Institute of Science, Department of Inorganic and Physical Chemistry, India

Publications

• Raghavendra Meena, Guanna Li, and Michele Casula. Ground-state properties of the narrowest zigzag graphene nanoribbon from quantum Monte Carlo and comparison with density functional theory.

J. Chem. Phys. 156, 084112 (2022).

Topic: Theoretical study of isonitrile coupling mediated by allenic diborenes.

• Sagar Ghorai, **Raghavendra Meena**, Anju P. Joseph, and Eluvathingal D. Jemmis. Comparison of RNC Coupling and CO Coupling Mediated by Cr-Cr Quintuple Bond and B-B Multiple Bonds: Main Group Metallomimetics. The Journal of Physical Chemistry A **2021** 125 (33), 7207-7216.

Skills

Modules GAUSSIAN, QuantumESPRESSO, TurboRVB (for QMC methods), VASP,

CP2K, ASE, and Blender.

Languages Basic: MATLAB, C++, and bash scripting

Intermediate: Python, and \LaTeX

Others 1) More than 4 years of experience in using supercomputing resources.

2) Linux/macOS/Windows environment.

Education

Oct 2020– Present PhD, Theoretical Chemistry

Wageningen University & Research, The Netherlands

May 2019– May 2020 Master's thesis, Computational Materials Science

Université Pierre et Marie Curie (UPMC, Sorbonne Université), Paris, France

Aug 2015– April 2020 BS-MS Dual Degree, Chemistry and Physics

Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Pune, Maharashtra, India

Grants/Awards/Scholarships

• Computational budget granted by NWO SURFsara on Snellius machine (1 x 500,000 SBUs and 2 x 1,000,000 SBUs).

• Erasmus+ inter-institutional credit mobility fellowship awarded by the European Union, 2019-2020.

- INSPIRE (Innovation in Science Pursuit for Inspired Research) Scholarship awarded by the Department of Science and Technology, India, 2015-2020.
- National Talent Search Scholarship (NTSE) Scholarship awarded by National Council for Educational Research and Training (NCERT), India, **July 2013**.

Certifications

- Oral presentations at NWO CHemistry As INnovativing Science (NWO-CHAINS)(2022; The Netherlands).
- Poster presentations at International Conference on Theoretical Aspects of Catalysis (ICTAC) (June 2022;
 Lyon, France.), Netherlands' Catalysis and Chemistry Conference (N3C) (May 2022; The Netherlands).
- Attendance at CECAM MolSim "Understanding Molecular Simulation" course (2023), Han-sur-Lesse winter school for theoretical & computational chemistry (2021), Paris International School on Advanced Computational Materials Science (PISACMS) (2021), and International Conference on Electrocatalysis for Energy Applications and Sustainable Chemicals (EcoCat) (2020) (online).

Teaching & Supervision

- Supervised 2 MSc Major & 1 MSc Minor thesis, and a BSc practical course in Bio-Organic Chemistry for Life Sciences.
- TA in the following courses: Computer modeling of biomolecules, Biofunctional food ingredients, structure & reactivity.